Finding Aid for Kinsley S. Bingham Papers, 1820-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kinsley S. Bingham Papers [microform] 1820-1944, 1820-1870
Bingham, Kinsley S. (Kinsley Scott), 1808-1861.
1 oversize folder on 4 microfilm rolls
1.25 linear feet
Michigan Democratic congressman, 1847-1851, Republican governor, 1855-1858, and U.S. Senator, 1859-1861; correspondence and genealogical papers of the Bingham and Warden families of Livingston County, including letters from Kinsley, his wife Mary Warden, his son James (First Lieutenant, Sixteenth Michigan Infantry, who died in 1862), and Robert Warden, Jr.; correspondence concerning family affairs, political and legislative matters, Bingham's inauguration in Lansing, Michigan, in 1857, and the Civil War; letters to Warden from friends in Scotland and Camillus, New York including one from Henry S. Sinn about slavery and the Civil War; and diary, 1862-1863, kept by Mrs. Bingham.
mf 314, mf 315, mf 316, mf 317
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These materials were acquired in several accessions between 1938-1955 from Janet Warden (donor no. 300 ), Emilie Comstock ( 1699 ), Roscoe O. Bonisteel ( 2035 ) and William W. Comstock ( 3135 ).
The collection is open for research.
The Bentley Historical Library holds the originals of the Bingham papers. For preservation reasons, researchers are required to use the microfilm edition of the papers. Access to the originals may be granted after consultation with the reference archivist.
Kinsley Scott Bingham was born to Calvin and Betsy (Scott) Bingham in Camillus, Onondaga County, New York on December 16, 1808. Kinsley S. Bingham received a strong education in New York, including the study of law with Gen. James R. Lawrence of Syracuse. He immigrated to Michigan Territory in 1833, where he established a farm in Livingston County. He quickly became involved in local government, serving as Justice of the Peace, Postmaster, and the 1st Judge of Probate for Livingston County. He was elected to the 1st Michigan State Legislature in 1837, and was re-elected for consecutive terms from 1838-1842, also serving as Speaker of the House in 1838, 1839 and 1842. He was then elected to Congress and served in the U.S. House of Representatives (Democrat) for two terms, 1847-1851. He returned to rural life for several years as a Free Soil Democrat and holding no political office, before being elected Governor of Michigan (Republican), 1855-1858. In 1859 he served in the U.S. Senate (Republican) until his death in 1861. Throughout his political service, he remained closely involved in the management of his farm, and was committed to representing rural interests.
In 1833 he married Margaret Warden, recently arrived in New York from Scotland, and they moved to Michigan with her brother, Robert Warden and family, to establish Green Oak in Livingston County. In 1834 their only child, Kinsley W. Bingham (1838-ca. 1908), was born, and Margaret died four days later. In 1839 he married Mary Warden, younger sister of his first wife, and in 1840 their only child was born, James W. Bingham (1840-1862).
Kinsley S. Bingham died at his home in Green Oak on October 5, 1861.
The Bingham papers are comprised of two series, Correspondence and Other Materials, reproduced on four rolls of microfilm. The Correspondence series includes personal letters (originals and typescripts) between members of the Bingham and Warden families. There is extensive correspondence (1848-1861) between Bingham and his wife, Mary Warden Bingham, during his absences while serving in government offices in Lansing, Michigan and Washington, D.C. There is also a substantial correspondence from James W. Bingham, writing to his parents during his boarding school years at the Normal School in Ypsilanti, Michigan and one year while studying at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. Later letters between James and his mother were written while James was serving with Co. H, 1st Michigan Infantry, and then in Co. B, 2nd Battalion, 16th U.S. Infantry. Also of interest are letters in 1850 referring to John, a nephew who participated in the California Gold Rush, where he died. The Other Materials series includes political speeches written by Kinsley S. Bingham, as well as newspaper clippings related to his death and memorial, and to the deaths of both of his sons. There is also genealogical notes made by family members for both the Bingham and Warden families, newspaper clippings about later family members, letters between extended family members, and miscellaneous and ephemeral materials.
Subjects:
Bingham, Kinsley S. (Kinsley Scott), 1808-1861.; Bingham family.; Camillus (N.Y.); Elections--Michigan--1856.; Governors--Michigan.; Livingston County (Mich.); Michigan State University.; Scotland.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 1st (1861). Company H.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Warden family.; Women--Michigan--Livingston County.
Contributors:
Bingham, James W., 1840-1862.; Bingham, Mary Warden.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes personal letters (both the original letters and typescripts) between members of the Bingham and Warden families. There is extensive correspondence (1848-1861) between Bingham and his wife, Mary Warden Bingham, during his absences while serving in government offices in Lansing, Michigan and Washington, D.C. There is also a substantial correspondence from James W. Bingham, writing to his parents during his boarding school years at the Normal School in Ypsilanti, Michigan and one year while studying at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. Later letters between James and his mother were written while James was serving with Co. H, 1st Michigan Infantry, and then in Co. B, 2nd Battalion, 16th U.S. Infantry. Also of interest are letters in 1850 referring to John, a nephew who participated in the California Gold Rush, where he died.
  - Undated, 2 folders (Reel 1)
  - Undated, transcripts (Reel 1)
  - 1820-1839 (Reel 1)
  - 1820-1839, transcripts (Reel 1)
  - 1840-1847 (Reel 1)
  - 1840-1847, transcripts (Reel 1)
  - 1848 January-Feb.
    - January-February 1848 (Reel 1)
    - March-April 1848 (Reel 1)
    - May-July, 1848 (Reel 1)
    - August-December 1848 (Reel 1)
  - 1848, transcripts (Reel 1)
  - 1849 (Reel 1)
  - 1849, transcripts (Reel 1)
  - 1850
    - January-June, 1850 (Reel 1)
    - July-December 1850 (Reel 2)
  - 1850, transcripts (Reel 2)
  - 1851-1854 (Reel 2)
  - 1851-1854, transcripts (Reel 2)
  - 1855-1857 (Reel 2)
  - 1855-1857, transcripts (Reel 2)
  - 1858-1860 (Reel 2)
  - 1858-1860, transcripts (Reel 2)
  - 1861
    - January-July, 1861 (Reel 2)
    - January-July, 1861, transcripts (Reel 2)
    - August-September, 1861 (Reel 2)
    - August-September, 1861, transcripts (Reel 3)
    - October-December, 1861 (Reel 3)
    - October-December, 1861, transcripts (Reel 3)
  - 1862
    - January-March, 1862 (Reel 3)
    - April-June, 1862 (Reel 3)
    - January-June, 1862, transcripts (Reel 3)
    - July-December 1862 (Reel 3)
    - July-December 1862, transcripts (Reel 3)
  - 1863-1870 (Reel 3)
  - 1863-1870, transcripts (Reel 3)
  - 1871-1909 (Reel 3)
  - 1871-1915, transcripts (Reel 3)
- Other Materials
  The Other Materials series includes a letter written in 1833 describing Livingston County, Michigan, and political speeches written by Kinsley S. Bingham, as well as newspaper clippings related to his death and memorial, and to the deaths of both of his sons. Two folders are related to James W. Bingham, including original compositions and speeches for school and additional transcripts of his letters. General information includes genealogical notes made by family members for both the Bingham and Warden families, newspaper clippings about later family members, letters between extended family members and miscellaneous and ephemeral materials. Also included is a journal kept by Mary Warden Bingham, which is divided into two sections. The diary portion notes her daily activities at Green Oak in 1862-1863. The accounts section provides detailed lists of household expenditures for 1871-1874. Certificates of commission and appointment related to Kinsley S. Bingham are filed separately in an oversize folder.
  - Genealogical material concerning the Bingham and Warden families undated (Reel 3)
  - Speeches of Kinsley S. Bingham undated (Reel 4)
  - Newspaper clippings regarding deaths of Kinsley S. Bingham, of James W. Bingham, and of Kinsley W. Bingham (Reel 4)
  - Letter from Kinsley S. Bingham describing Livingston County, Michigan 1833, transcripts (Reel 4)
  - Miscellanea 1839-1944 (Reel 4)
  - James W. Bingham letters, 1856-1862, typescripts (Reel 4)
  - Compositions and Speeches of James W. Bingham undated (Reel 4)
  - Letters of Bingham-Warden families 1841-1915 (Reel 4)
    William W. Comstock, donor
  - Newspaper Clippings 1914-1939 (Reel 4)
  - Volume of Mary Warden Bingham containing diary, 1862-1863 and household accounts, 1871-1874 (Reel 4)
  - Commissions and Appointments of Kinsley S. Bingham, 5 items (Folder AC)